飞了150万公里后
After a 1.5 million kilometer journey,
JWST终于到达日地L2点晕轨道
the James Webb Space Telescope has arrived at the Sun Earth L2 point.
它在最后执行了中段修正点火(MCC) "MCC-2"
It did this by executing its final Mid-Course Correction burn called "MCC-2".
点火持续297秒 不到五分钟
It lasted just 297 seconds, or a little less than five minutes,
速度只改变了1.5m/s
and it only changed Webb's speed by about 1.5 m/s.
速度增量和人快步走差不多
That's a brisk walking pace.
看起来不多 但足够让JWST进入环绕L2点的轨道了
It may not seem like much, but it was enough to place Webb into an orbit around L2.
实际上它进入的轨道尺寸相当之大
In fact, it placed it into a very large orbit,
大概是月球绕地轨道的两倍左右
one that's more than twice as large as the Moon's orbit around Earth!
JWST大约需要六个月才能绕L2一周
It'll take Webb about six months to complete a single orbit around L2,
它第一圈的旅途中排满了各项镜面校准、调相
and this first go-around is jam packed with mirror alignments, phasing,
仪器校准、移动目标跟踪测试、认证、轨道保持机动
instrument calibrations, moving target tracking tests, verifications, station keeping maneuvers,
最后才能迎来科学观测
and finally, the first science observations.
可L2点到底有什么特别的?
But what exactly is so special about L2?
它只是茫茫宇宙中孤零零一个什么都没有的点呀
I mean, it's just a point in space, and it's an empty point in space at that.
JWST是如何围绕一个什么都没有的点的?
So how can Webb orbit something that isn't there?
诚然L2点什么都没有 但环绕这样一个点运行的天体在宇宙中并不少见
Well, it is true that L2 is empty, but orbiting empty points in space is actually very common.
这是因为只要有两个大质量的天体在相互作用运行
And that's because whenever there are two massive bodies that are orbiting each other,
它们都会围绕一个共同的质心或"重心"运行
they both orbit a common center of mass or "barycenter".
如果物体的质量足够大 那么质心就位于两者之间
If the objects are massive enough, the center of mass lies somewhere in between.
大家都说月球绕地球转 那是因为两者质心位于地球内部
We only say that the Moon orbits Earth because its center of mass is located inside Earth.
但是冥王星和卡戎的质量相似
But Pluto and Charon have similar masses,
所以两者质心就在之间的某个地方
so their barycenter is somewhere in the space between them.
因此 天体可以围绕太空中什么都没有的点运转没什么稀奇
So the fact that something can orbit an empty point space really isn't all that unusual,
但别忘了 我们之前说的是二体系统
but at the same time, that's a two-body system.
还是不能解释JWST如何能围绕二体系统之外的某个点运行
It doesn't explain how Webb can orbit a point that's outside of another two-body system.
还好我们可以把这个问题拆开来
Well, the good news is that we can break this problem down
先了解L2点是什么 再来说JWST如何围绕它运行
and understand just what the L2 point is and how Webb can orbit around it.
实际上有很多航天器都曾环绕过L2点运行
In fact, there are many spacecraft that have orbited L2,
比如NASA的威尔金森微波各向异性探测器(WMAP)
such as NASA's WMAP Satellite
ESA的普朗克巡天者与赫歇尔空间天文台
and ESA's Planck and Herschel telescopes,
俄罗斯与德国研制的Spektr-RG ESA的盖亚号探测器
and Russia's Spektr-RG and ESA's Gaia spacecraft
它们现在都还在L2点环绕轨道
are both orbiting there today.
工商时间 跳转2:58
那么有没有一款……
In fact, Gaia is featured in an episode of "Space The New Frontier",
which is a series on Magellan TV, who I'd like to thank for sponsoring today's video.
With more than 3,000 documentaries on nature, history, space science and technology,
Magellan TV always has something amazing to watch.
New documentaries are added each week and are presented without commercial interruption.
And now Magellan is offering my viewers a full month of their award winning content absolutely free!
Just use the link in the description of this video.
L2是日地五个拉格朗日点之一
L2 is one of the five Lagrangian points between the Sun and Earth.
实际上 这样的五点存在于任意二体系统中
Actually, these five points exist around any two-body system.
因此地月系也有自己的拉格朗日点
So there are Lagrangian points for the Earth-Moon system,
太阳-木星系统也有
a set of points for the Sun-Jupiter system, and so on.
如果此时有第三个物体放在这些点上
Now, if a third object is placed at any of these points,
那么两个大天体的重力合力会使第三个物体相对于其他两者保持稳定
the gravitational forces of the two large bodies combine in such a way
that holds the third object stable with respect to the others.
结果就是第三物体会跟随前两者一同环绕运行
The practical upshot is that as the system orbits, the third body tags along.
因此 日地L1点非常适合需要时刻面对太阳的任务
And that's why the Sun-Earth L1 point is a great place to position Sun-facing missions like
比如太阳和太阳圈探测器
the Solar Heliospheric Observatory
或者要时刻面对地球的任务 比如DSCOVR
and Earth-facing missions like DSCOVR.
同样 L2点适合一些天体物理相关的任务 比如盖亚号和JWST
Likewise, L2 is the place to put astrophysics missions like Gaia and Webb.
在这两点上 航天器可以与地球保持持续的可视通信
At both locations, spacecraft maintain a constant line of sight communication with Earth,
不用关心地球公转的问题
even as Earth orbits the Sun.
但L2点对于JWST来说非常重要
But L2 is particularly important for Webb,
因为在那里 JWST只需一个遮阳罩就能同时阻挡来自太阳地球月球的热量
because it can block the heat of the Sun, Earth, and Moon with a single sunshield.
红外天文观测的绝佳之地
That's a perfect place for infrared astronomy.
但也有一些重要的注意事项
But there are some important caveats.
首先 第三个物体的质量相对于较大的天体来说必须非常非常非常小
For one thing, the third object has to have a mass that's really³ small relative to the larger bodies.
这显然没问题
Obviously, that's not a problem.
JWST的质量远小于地球 更不用说太阳了
Webb's mass is negligible compared to Earth, let alone the Sun.
但另一个注意事项是 拉格朗日点通常被称为"亚稳定的"
But the other caveat is that the Lagrangian points are at best described as metastable,
尤其是L1 L2 L3三点
especially the first three points.
要理解我说的 大家可以想象这样一个光滑无摩擦的马鞍形面
To understand what I mean, imagine a saddle that's perfectly smooth and frictionless.
想象你要把一个玻璃球放在中心这个位置
Now imagine trying to balance a marble in the very center of the saddle.
理论上是可能的 但实际操作起来可太难了
It's theoretically possible, but as a practical matter, it's extremely hard to do.
L2点的不稳定就是类似的情况
The L2 point is a lot like this.
沿垂直于日地连线运动的物体会向中心落下(视频中红色箭头)
An object moving perpendicular to the Sun-Earth line falls toward the center.
而之后它会向接近或者远离地球的方向移动(视频中蓝色箭头)
But then it either falls toward or away from Earth.
而如果JWST远离了地球 那就麻烦了
Now, if Webb falls away from Earth, it's really in trouble,
因为那时只能让JWST调转方向点火才能把望远镜带回来
because the only way to bring it back would be to turn it around and thrust back.
而这样会导致望远镜瞬间升温
But that will cause the telescope to suddenly warm up.
所有结构都会突然膨胀 粘胶都突然融掉 任务失败
All of the structures would expand, glues and adhesives would melt, and the mission would be over.
空降百亿补贴了属实是
And that's bad.
JWST的发动机安装在观测平台的阳面
Webb has thrusters only on the warm Sun-facing side of the observatory.
因为发动机的热量和尾气会影响望远镜的阴面温度
And that's because hot thrusters would contaminate the cold telescope's side with heat
尾气还可能冷凝在镜面上
or with rocket exhaust that would otherwise condense on the optics.
也是万万不行的
That would also be bad.
一个相对安全的方法是把JWST送到 但没完全送到L2点
A safer approach is to place Webb almost, but not quite at L2.
这样当它要落回地球的时候 就轻轻点火把它推回去
And that way, when it falls back toward Earth, a tiny thruster burn pushes it back almost,
但也不要推到飞过L2点的程度
but not quite back to L2.
这样能保证JWST不会有飞出L2点的风险 因为那样就无力回天了
And this means Webb never runs the risk of actually falling beyond L2, where it cannot be recovered.
因此 阿丽亚娜五号火箭也是刻意设计让最终能量差一点
And that's why the Ariane V launch was intentionally designed to slightly undershoot
让航天器自行进行之后一系列的中段修正点火
and let the spacecraft do a series of Mid Course Correction burns.
前两次点火 MCC-1a和MCC-1b 是在去L2点路上进行的
The first two, MCC-1a and MCC-1b, were executed on the way out to L2.
但到达接近L2点的话 会出现另一个问题
However, arriving even just shy of L2 leaves us with another problem.
在这个距离上 太阳处于被地球永久环食的状态
At that distance, the Sun is in a permanent annular eclipse by Earth.
而JWST是太阳能驱动的
Webb is solar powered.
倒是可以用核能 但那样又贵又难做
Now it could use nuclear power, but that's expensive and hard to do.
另一个复杂的问题是 科里奥利力会导致韦伯在L2点附近出现偏移
Another complication is that Coriolis forces would cause Webb to liberate around L2.
简言之 JWST最后会进入一个很小的L2点环绕轨道
In other words, Webb would find itself in a tiny orbit around L2
需要更多的点火才能保持位置
that would need even more thruster burns to manage.
同时 月球的重力也不能忽略
Oh, and the Moon's gravity on Webb is also still a thing,
而且月球绕地球的公转导致它的引力随时都在变
and it's constantly varying as it orbits Earth.
事实证明 这些现实世界的复杂问题只需改用环绕L2的大轨道就能解决
It turns out that these real-world complications can be addressed by simply taking up a large orbit around L2.
可让航天器环绕一个什么都没有的点又是怎么做到的?
But how is it possible to orbit something that isn't there?
毕竟L2点仍然是茫茫太空中一个虚空的点
I mean, L2 is still an empty point in space.
为了让大家更好地理解此事
Well, to help us understand better,
我们一起来看看JWST上一共受到了哪些力
let's look at the problem by considering some of the forces acting on Webb.
如果JWST就在L2点 那它会受到来自太阳和地球的重力
If Webb were actually at L2, it would be feeling gravitational forces from the Sun and from Earth.
我们把这两个力分开画以便区分
So let's draw them separately so that we can keep track of them.
JWST同时还在围绕太阳公转
Now, Webb is orbiting the Sun at the same time,
所以会有一个让JWST往外甩的 与前两个力反方向的离心力
so we can also imagine a centrifugal force pulling Webb in the opposite direction.
L2点有意思的就是 在这个距离时
Now, the great thing about L2 is that at this distance,
离心力刚好等于地球与太阳的重力之和
the centrifugal force is exactly balanced by the gravity of the Earth and Sun.
你们可能听过不存在"离心力"这样的力 的确没错
Now, you may have heard that there is no such thing as a centrifugal force, and that is correct,
但我们在这里讨论的是一个旋转的非惯性系
but we are talking about a rotating non inertial frame here,
所以离心力这个概念仍然是总结所有力的实际效果的一个有用方法
so centrifugal forces are still a useful way of summarizing all of the real effects that are going on.
另外我们这里不考虑月球的重力影响
Oh, and we're not going to worry about the gravitational effects of the Moon or
现实情况里太阳和地球也不能考虑成质点
even the fact that the Sun and the Earth are not point sources.
我们现在只考虑最简单的情况
We're just going to keep everything simple for the time being.
现在我们把JWST从L2点稍稍拿开
Now let's move Webb up some distance away from L2.
太阳的重力方向会有极其微小的变化
The gravitational force from the Sun changes a tiny amount,
但不会太大 毕竟太阳有1.5亿公里远呢
but not very much because it's over 150 million kilometers away.
而地球距离是其百分之一 所以重力方向变化会很明显
But Earth is just 1% of that distance, so its gravity changes considerably.
且JWST此时离地球更远了 所以重力大小也会有所减小
Because Webb is now farther away from Earth, its gravitational pull gets weaker.
方向也不再与太阳重力方向平行
It's also no longer parallel with the Sun's direction, either.
所以我们把地球重力方向分解成X和Y方向
So let's break it up into its X and Y components.
于是问题来了
Now we can really see the problem.
离心力方向是沿X轴的
The centrifugal force is in the X direction of our diagram,
它已经比地球与太阳在X方向上的合力要大了
but it's actually greater than the gravitational forces from the Sun and Earth.
说明JWST要向远处漂移远离L2点了
That means Webb is going to drift both down and farther away from L2.
因此我们需要在X和Y方向上对这个漂移进行修正
So we need to fix this drift in both the X and Y directions.
首先 让JWST向地球靠近一点点
First, we bring Webb a little closer to Earth
此时它停留在一个新的点上方 我们称为L2'
so that it's now hovering above a new point that we'll just call L2'.
此时地球的重力变大 X方向的分量又能平衡离心力了
Earth's gravity gets stronger, and its X component helps to balance the centrifugal force once again.
但Y方向的分量也随之变大了
But the Y component has gotten stronger as well.
所以JWST会倾向于向"下"移动
So Webb wants to move downward.
但随着JWST向下移动接近日地连线
But the closer it gets to the Sun Earth line,
地球的重力就会变大 JWST就又回往地球方向飞去
the stronger Earth's gravity gets and the more it moves toward Earth.
我们不希望这样
We can't let that happen, either,
因为那样会增加遮阳罩的负荷
because then the heat load would become too strong for the sunshield to handle.
所以我们可以给JWST一个垂直纸面向里的速度
However, we can counteract this downward force by giving Webb a sideways push into the screen.
创造一个新的离心力来平衡地球重力在Y方向的分量
This sets up a new centrifugal force that balances the downward force of Earth's gravity.
此处勘误: F c_halo = F ⊕y
加上一个这样的旋转运动 JWST就进入环绕L2'的晕轨道了
When combined with the sideways motion, Webb takes up a new circular halo orbit around L2-prime.
此处勘误: F c_halo = F ⊕y
也就是说L2'点并不需要存在一个有实际质量的物体吸引JWST
And that means there doesn't have to be a physical mass at L2-Prime in order to attract Webb.
相反 JWST只需要靠地球重力的Y方向分量就能抵消离心力
Rather, Webb is simply being pulled by the Y component of Earth's gravitational force.
当然 这里对于JWST如何环绕L2的解释是极度简化的
Now this is an oversimplified discussion of Webb's orbit around L2.
为了方便大家理解JWST如何环绕一个虚空的点
We deliberately ignored real-world complications in order to understand
我们刻意忽略了真实世界中各种复杂情况
how Webb can orbit something that isn't there.
但是要进入JWST的实际轨道
But getting into Webb's actual orbit
你就必须考虑到所有现实世界中的复杂情况
required taking all of these real-world complications into account.
所以为了方便 JWST并不是瞄着L2点飞的
So to make things easier, Webb wasn't actually launched to L2.
而是瞄着L2旁边一侧飞的
Instead, it was launched to a point along the side of L2.
在JWST刚要开始掉出轨道时
As it was starting to fall away,
JWST会执行MCC-2点火 进入自己的轨道
Webb executed its MCC-2 burn to settle into its orbit.
由于这个初始掉出轨道的分量是以X方向指向地球的
Since part of this initial fall was directed in the X direction toward Earth,
所以点火后 JWST进入的轨道倾斜了大约33度
the burn propelled Webb into an orbit that's now tilted by about 33 degrees.
轨道本身也不是圆形 而是椭圆的形状
The orbit isn't perfectly circular either, but rather follows an elliptical shape.
最后的结果就是 JWST到L2点的距离从25万公里到83.2万公里不等
As a result, Webb's distance from the L2 point varies between 250,000 km and 832,000 km.
作为参考 月球轨道的半长轴是40万公里左右
Now, for reference, the Moon's semi-major axis is about 400,000 kilometers,
可见JWST环绕L2的轨道有多大了
so Webb's orbit around L2 is enormous!
选择这样巨大的轨道可以让前往L2更加简单
This large orbit was chosen because it makes getting to L2 a lot easier.
物体离环绕点越远
The farther something is from its orbital focus,
运行速度就越慢 机动所需能量就越小
the slower it moves and the less energy is required to maneuver.
也因此MCC-2只点火了5分钟 消耗DV仅1.5m/s
And that's why it only took a five-minute burn and a 1.5 meters per second Delta-V.
更大的轨道还能保证JWST不会落入地球或月球的阴影中
The larger orbit also means that
Webb will never drift into the shadows of the Earth or the Moon during its mission.
但过大的轨道可能让来自地球或月球的杂光漏过太阳罩
However, larger orbits can permit stray light from the Earth or Moon to get past the sunshield
到达主镜副镜
and reach the primary or secondary mirrors.
还可能减少与深空网络的通信机会
In addition, a larger orbit
can reduce the number of communication opportunities with the Deep Space Network.
因此JWST必须经常调整朝向
That's why Webb will have to change its orientation
保证在整个轨道上始终不会有杂光影响光学侧元件
to keep stray light off the mirrors at all times throughout its orbit
并妥善安排通信下行链路
and schedule the communication downlinks accordingly.
JWST环绕L2点一圈大约需要六个月
Webb takes about six months to complete one orbit around L2.
虽然它偶尔会飞出L2点
Although it sometimes flies out just a little bit past this point.
但轨道的几何中心仍然位于更靠近地球的L2'点
The geometric center of the orbit is still centered on the L2-prime point on the Earth side.
记住 我们不能让这个球刚好停在马鞍的正中心
Remember, we don't want that ball right at the very middle of the saddle.
因此JWST会经常进行位置保持点火来维持轨道
That's why Webb will execute small stationkeeping burns every now and then to maintain its orbit.
盖亚号这样的任务每年需要三到四次的点火
Missions like Gaia only require three to four of these burns every year.
但JWST的点火则更加频繁 原因有几个
But Webb will require much more frequent burns for a couple of reasons.
其一 JWST的遮阳罩会持续受到太阳光压影响
For one, its sunshield is always feeling a torque from solar radiation pressure.
JWST可以靠旋转自身的动量轮来平衡这个转动的力
Webb can counter this rotational force by spinning up its reaction wheels.
但太阳光压是一个持续的作用
But the solar radiation pressure is unrelenting,
所以动量轮的转速会一点点变快
so the reaction wheels must increase their spin over time.
最终就需要进行一次位置保持点火来让JWST转回原来的位置
Eventually, a station-keeping burn is required to rotate Webb back into place
让动量轮减速 释放能量
and let the wheels throttle back.
JWST还会在改变观测对象的时候改变指向
Webb also changes its orientation as it points from one position to the other.
所有这些动作都会对JWST的轨道带来轻微的扰动
All of these motions perturb Webb's orbit ever so slightly,
也就需要更多的位置保持点火
requiring more station-keeping burns to maintain.
因此 JWST需要每21天进行一次这样的点火
And that's why Webb executes a burn once every 21 days.
点火的时刻与持续时间都是由NASA哥达德太空飞行中心的飞行动力小组计算的
The exact timing and duration of those burns are calculated by the Flight Dynamics Team
at NASA's Goddard Space Flight Center.
他们将通过监测JWST的遥测数据
They'll do this by monitoring Webb's telemetry data
并使用来自深空网络的测距数据
and using ranging data from the Deep Space Network
来确定JWST的位置与运动情况 来完成计算
to pinpoint Webb's location and its motion at all times.
计算过程还会考虑来自月球  甚至是其他行星的引力扰动
They even take into account gravitational perturbations from the Moon
and even the gravitational perturbations of the rest of the planets!
所以 飞行动力小组那帮人挺牛逼的
So, yeah, the flight dynamics team are really awesome,
未来大概……20年吧 可有得忙了~
and they've got their work cut out for them over the next...20 years?
后面是片尾工商 感谢观看~
And speaking of amazing teams, how about these amazing folks are helping to keep Launch Pad Astronomy going,
and I'd like to welcome Marcel Barros, Steve C, Joe Curley, Timothy Fudge,
Chris Gregory, Erik Johnson, now Navaneetha Krishna, Barry Stott, and Lucy Thursfield as my newest patrons.
And if you'd like to join me on this journey through this amazing universe of ours,
well, please make sure you subscribe and ring that notification bell so that you don't miss out on any new videos.
Until next time, stay curious, my friend.